(
"ai_sub_version": "3.5.2",
"generated_at": "2026-08-19T06:18:17.548745",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
甘くて幸せなこと
Something so sweet and happy,
隠し味何にしよう
What should we use as a secret ingredient?
純粋な乙女心
A pure maiden's heart,
甘い恋も絡めなくちゃ
We've got to entangle sweet love into it too!
切なさ重ねてミルフィーユ
Layering sadness like a mille-feuille,
酸味も積み上げタルト
Building up the tart with sourness too,
苦味もチョコレートケーキ？
Bitterness too, like a chocolate cake?
魔法かけた甘い奇跡
A sweet miracle cast with magic!
甘さを抑えてビターとか
Holding back the sweetness for something bitter, or
ミルクなしのコーヒーとか
Coffee without any milk or anything...
甘いだけじゃ大人になれないの？
Can't you become an adult just by being sweet?
そんなの絶対に絶対いやいやいや
There's no way, absolutely no, no, no way!
ねえあげようか 甘い罠
Hey, shall I give you a sweet trap?
ほら虜にしてあげる
Look, I'll make you captive.
そんな魔法かけるから
Because I'll cast a magic like that,
ちょっとだけ待たせたげるわ
I'll make you wait just a little bit!
ねえ気づいてるんでしょ？
Hey, do you realize it?
隠し味の恋心
The secret ingredient of romantic feelings,
苦味とか酸味とか
Like bitterness, or sourness...
たった一口が足りなくて
Because just one bite wasn't enough,
赤いイチゴみたい意地張って
I act stubborn like a red strawberry,
甘いところなんて見せないわ
I won't show you my sweet side.
完璧に作るもん
I'll make it perfectly,
一人でも、でも、でも
even all by myself, but, but, but...
ねえ 気づいてるんでしょ？
Hey, didn't you notice?
わかってるんでしょ？
Didn't you know?
隠し味の恋心
Love is the secret ingredient.
苦味とか 酸味とか
Bitterness, acidity...
そういうのもたまにはいいわ
Those are nice sometimes too.
意地っ張りで ワガママな そんな「甘い魔法」使い
Being stubborn and selfish, I use this 'sweet magic'.
たった一口が足りなくて
Because just one bite wasn't enough,
まだ足りない？
Still not enough?
迷子 迷子 真っ只中 さあ
Lost, lost, right in the middle, come on.
パ パ パラ パーライア 「ア」
Pa-pa-para paranoia, 'ah'!
ギコ ギコ MY HEART (こころ) 選定
Creeak, creeak, my heart selected.
パ パ パラ パーライア 「ア」
Pa-pa-para paranoia, 'ah'!
退路 退路 断ったから 絡まった
Escape route cut off, getting tangled up.
パ パ パラ パーライア 「ア」
Pa-pa-para paranoia, 'ah'!
sad sad 突っ伏して カラ
Sad, sad, face down, empty.
ぱ ぱ ぱ la ぱー ら のーい 「ド」
Pa-pa-pa-la-paranoia, 'do'!
さあ バ バ バグ さ バグバグ
Now, it's a bug, bug, bug!
タ タ タグ 才能 の タグ
Tagged, tagged, talent tagged.
もう ハ ハ 剥ぐ 感情 は 剥ぐ
Peeling, peeling emotions away.
発症 「クルシイ」は 嫌 嫌 嫌 嫌 嫌 嫌
The onset of 'pain' is so hateful.
まあ ！ 絶叫 な 感情 落下 パッパ ラノイア 「ア」
Well! Screaming emotions falling, paranoia.
溺れ声 上げては くるくる
Raising a drowned voice, round and round.
まあ ⚠️ 絶体絶命 落下 やった ラ滅 多ラ
Desperate situation, falling no matter what.
沈め ユメ ユメ 嫌 嫌 嫌
Sink, dreams, I hate it.
さあ バ バ バグ さ バグバグ
Now, it's a bug, bug, bug!
的 ハズレズレ 慈愛 嫌 嫌
Off the mark, affection, I hate it.
さあ バ バ バグ さ バグバグ
Now, it's a bug, bug, bug!
解答 絶え絶え 嫌 嫌 嫌 嫌 嫌 嫌
Answers fading out, I hate it!
狂狂 パッカン 警報
Mad, mad, open up, alarm!
待って 無理 くるくる ゼロで回れ
Wait, impossible, spin from zero.
ああ パッカン ほら やっぱ
Ah, open up, see, as expected.
無理 くるくる 愛より二人
Impossible, spin, two people over love.
エンドレス 病み … ？
Endless sickness...?
抱っこ 抱っこ いらない 子だ
Cuddles, cuddles, an unwanted child.
パ パ パラ パーライア 「ア」
Pa-pa-para paranoia, 'ah'!
いい子 いい子 「頑張れ」の 氾濫
Good boy, good boy, a flood of 'do your best'.
アドミニストレイター 呻呼
Administrator groaning.
さあ バ バ バグ さ バグバグ
Now, it's a bug, bug, bug!
ラ ラ ラグ ランタイムラグ
Lag, lag, runtime lag.
ロ ロ ログ 抗 の ログ
Log, log, log of resistance.
バ バ バグ パッパパラ パッパ パラノイア
Bug, bug, pa-pa-para-paranoia.
絶叫 な 感情 落下 パッパ ラノイア 「ア」
Screaming emotions falling, paranoia.
左 右 行方も くるくる
Left and right, where to go, spinning around.
悲惨 ⚠️ 限界 脳 狂っちまっ て やった ラ滅 多ラ
Tragic, limit brain, going crazy.
闇迷え 酔え イナイ イナイ バ
Get lost in darkness, get drunk, peek-a-boo.
イナイ イナイ バッテン
Peek-a-boo, cross out.
絶叫 な 感情 落下 パッパ ラノイア 「ア」
Screaming emotions falling, paranoia.
溺れ声 上げては くるくる
Raising a drowned voice, round and round.
まあ ⚠️ 絶体絶命 落下 やった ラ滅 多ラ
Desperate situation, falling no matter what.
凍え 枯れ果て 嫌 嫌 嫌
Frozen and withered away, I hate it.
さあ バ バ バグ さ バグバグ
Now, it's a bug, bug, bug!
爛れ 荒れ荒れ 悲哀 嫌 嫌
Festering, rough sorrow, I hate it.
さあ バ バ バグ さ バグバグ
Now, it's a bug, bug, bug!
暗闇 (クロ) マミレ 理性 嫌 嫌 嫌 今 今 今 嫌 嫌 嫌
Reason coated in darkness, I hate it, now, now, now!
というわけで、皆さま、こんばんは！風真いろはです！
With that said, good evening everyone! I'm Kazama Iroha!
ホロライブ6期生、ホロックスのルイーズ…侍の風真いろはでござるよー！
I am Kazama Iroha, the samurai and secret society member of Hololive 6th generation, HoloX!
というわけで、本日は誕生日の生誕ライブにお越しいただき、ありがとうございます！
With that said, thank you very much for coming to my birthday live today!
今日のことはですね…ここが…これです！風真いろは生誕ライブ2023で…
Today's event is... right here... this is it! Kazama Iroha's Birthday Live 2023...
たくさんね、スクリーン外とか、感想とかいっぱい、いっぱい、つぶやいてくださいね！
Please tweet lots of your thoughts and impressions!
はい、というわけで早速ね、2曲続けて歌って踊らせていただきました！
So, without further ado, we just had two songs sung and danced!
「スイートマジック」と「バグ」でしたー！
"Sweet Magic" and "Bug"!
歌も踊りもめちゃくちゃ頑張りました！
I worked super hard on both singing and dancing!
頑張って、みんな絞り出しちゃった、最初から。
I put everything into it right from the very beginning.
はい、ちょっとね、昨日のカウントダウンではケーキを食べて過ごしちゃったござんなんですが、
Yesterday during the countdown, I spent my time eating cake,
まずはステージのね、紹介をしていきたいと思います。後ろにケーキが見えてるもんね！
but first, let's introduce the stage! You can see the cake right behind me!
というわけでステージ！みなさま、見てください！
So everyone, please take a look at the stage!
今回、誕生日ライブ用にこしらえていただいたわーい！でっかいケーキ！食べたい！
This huge cake was specially made for my birthday live! I want to eat it!
昨日食べ損ねたんですけど、みなさんはいまケーキ食べたりなんか美味しいものとか飲んだり、食べたりしながらライブを見てくださっているんでしょうか？
I missed out on eating cake yesterday, but are you guys watching while eating cake or something delicious?
このね、1時間は全力で語るのもみなこと楽し、楽しみまして
I'm going to give this one hour my all to have fun with you all,
まずので、最後まで楽しみにしていてくださいね！
so please look forward to it until the very end!
はあ、激しくてまだ滑舌が回ってないんですけど。
Whew, it's so intense my tongue is still getting tied.
そして今回はですね、誕生日ということで、なんと今日のためにゲストの方からメッセージをいただいているという
And since today is my birthday, I've actually received messages from guests just for today,
ことで、今日一日それがソワソワしているんですけれども、
so I've been feeling restless all day today,
まだね、風も見てないんですよ、そのメッセージ！なのでちょっと、どんな内容かウキウキソワソワゴージャスゴージャスなんですけど、
but I haven't seen the message yet! So I'm all excited, nervous, and curious about what's inside,
え、そろそろ来るのかな？大丈夫かな？楽しみ、あ、来た来た来た来た！
um, is it coming soon? Will it be okay? I'm excited—oh, it's coming!
きましたね！早速1つ目のメッセージが届いたようでございます！
It's here! It looks like the first message has arrived!
風真殿の！風真殿の！
Lady Kazama! Lady Kazama!
聞こえました。
I heard you.
響いて感じて考えてますか？
Are you feeling, hearing, and thinking about it?
白上は今、月にいます。
Shirakami is on the moon right now.
やばい！涙、涙。
Oh no! Tears, tears.
なんか遠くに赤いモヤモヤとかお城っぽいなとか、近くにうさぎがいっぱいいるんですけども、そんな空間に来ております！
It's like there's a red haze and castle-like things far away, and lots of rabbits nearby, and I've come to such a space!
風真殿、お誕生日おめでとうございます！やったー！
Lady Kazama, happy birthday! Yay!
嬉しいな！
I'm so happy!
まさか足元にあと石ころをけてしまいました。
Oh no, I just stubbed my toe on a rock at my feet.
いや、風間殿ってのはやっぱりこのこれに関連するゲームのお話でいっぱい盛り上がったりとかできたので、
Well, with Lady Kazama, we've had so much fun getting excited talking about games related to this,
本当それが一番嬉しかったですね。白上はやはり共通の趣味を持っている仲間というのは良い。
and that made me really happy. It's great to have a companion who shares the same hobby.
分かる？またね、ゲーム内でもいいですし、ちょっとね、一緒にコンサートにも行った仲なので、
You know? Also, inside games is fine, and since we've also been to a concert together,
楽しかったですね。また、あのカフェとかも一緒にね、1回行ったけども、またぜひ行きましょう！
it was fun. Also, we went to a cafe together once, let's definitely go again!
エンチャント！
Enchant!
ということでね、ちょっとそっちの方に今から白上、エンチャントテレポートするから受け止めとくれ！
So, Shirakami is going to teleport to that side with enchant now, so catch me!
エンチャントテレポート！どこ？
Enchant teleport! Where?
どこでもいいですよ！飛んでった！
Anywhere is fine! She flew away!
どっから来るんだ？
Where is she coming from?
しんでしまうとはなさけない！
It's pathetic to die here!
3、2、1、GO！
3, 2, 1, GO!
ああ、何？HEEL？何事じゃ？
Oh, what? HEEL? What's going on?
うん、姫様がさらわれました！
Um, the princess has been kidnapped!
勇者は？
And the hero?
いません。
Absent.
うん、そうか！かくなる上はお前が勇者だ！
Well then! In that case, you are the hero!
設定崩壊…！！
Lore broken...!
「さあ、その宝箱の中身とこのなきなしの金で旅立って仲間を探して化け物倒して…」 (…適当じゃねえか)
"Now, set off on a journey with this treasure chest and meager gold to find companions and defeat monsters..." (...Arbitrary much?)
「とにもかくにも困ったら町のひとに話しかけようぜ？ボスとか全然倒せる！倒せる！マ・ジ・デ！」
"Anyway, if you're in trouble, talk to townspeople! Bosses are totally beatable! Seriously!"
いばって いばって いばって 当然 だって実際に一番偉いから
Strutting, strutting, strutting, naturally, because I'm the greatest!
人ごとみたいに言ってくれるぜ まったくもって上から目線すぎだぜ…
You say it like it's someone else's problem, looking down on us way too much...
経験値 経験値 経験値 積んで もっと屈強な仲間探したまえ！
Accumulate EXP, EXP, EXP, go find some tougher companions!
ていうか私は一兵卒です 有給休暇がデリート！デリート！
I mean, I'm just a foot soldier, my paid leave is DELETED! DELETED!
あなたがラスボスを倒してくる日を楽しみにして待っているぞい！
I'm looking forward to the day you defeat the final boss!
世界平和を取り戻すため お国の平和を守るため 一番後ろで指揮をとります あなたの経験値を伝えましょう
To restore world peace, to protect our country's peace, I will command from the back and pass on your EXP!
あなたのために 世界のために 戦う僕らの愛国心
For your sake, for the world's sake, our patriotism as we fight.
仲間も死んで絶滅寸前 やっぱりレベルが足りねぇ…orz
Companions died, on the verge of extinction, I guess our level isn't high enough... orz
あなたのパーティは 全滅しました。
Your party has been wiped out.
おお、神様な！アーメン
Oh, dear gods! Amen.
Oh...
しんでしまうとはなさけない！
It's pathetic to die!
3.2.1…×××!!
3, 2, 1... XXX!!
「王!」
"King!"
「なに?」
"What?"
「HELP!」
"HELP!"
「何事じゃ」
"What is it?"
「ひっ、姫がさらわれましたぁ」
"H-Hic, the princess has been kidnapped!"
「勇者は?」
"Where's the hero?"
「いません」
"None to be found."
「うーん、そうだな!かくなる上はお前が勇者だ」
"Hmm, I see! In that case, you are the hero!"
設定崩壊・…!!
Setting collapse...!!
「さあ、その宝箱の中身とこのなけなしの金で旅立って仲間を探して化け物倒して…」
"Now, take the contents of that chest and your meager coin, set off, find companions, defeat monsters..."
(……適当じゃねえか)
(That's so haphazard!)
「とにかく困ったら町のひとたちに話しかけようぜ?ボスとか全然倒せる!倒せる!マ・ジ・デ!」
"Anyway, if you're in trouble, talk to the townsfolk! You can totally beat bosses! Seriously!"
いばって いばって いばって
Acting so high and mighty,
当然だって実際に一番偉いから
naturally, because you're actually the most important one.
人ごとみたいに言ってくれるぜ
You say it like it's someone else's problem,
まったくもって上から目線すぎぜ
way too patronizing altogether.
経験値 経験値 経験値 積んで
Gather experience points, experience points, experience points,
もっと屈強な仲間探したまえ!
and go find tougher companions!
ていうか私は一兵卒です
I mean, I'm just a foot soldier,
有給休暇がデリート!デリート!
and my paid leave is deleted, deleted!
「あなたがラスボスを倒してくる日を楽しみにしておくぞい!」
"I'll be looking forward to the day you defeat the final boss!"
世界平和を取り戻す為、
To restore world peace,
お国の平和を守る為、
to protect the country's peace,
一番後ろに身を閉じ込め
shutting myself away at the very back,
致死率は目に見えた
the fatality rate is clear as day.
さあ検診のため お金のために 戦う王様何をみる
Now, for checkups, for money, what does the fighting king look at?
この絵も瀕死で絶滅寸前
This picture too is on the verge of extinction,
しんでしまうとはなさけない！
it's pathetic to die!
世界平和を取り戻す為、
To restore world peace,
あなたの笑顔を守る為、
to protect your smile,
魔法くん 幻想を
little wizard, illusions
独りからからに書き集め
written and gathered all alone,
本日は今日とて死んだふりしてステイする
today pretending to be dead and staying,
本物の勇者を待っている
waiting for the true hero.
掘りっと 掘りっと 掘りっとばっか
Just digging and digging and digging,
それは掘りっとばっかでばっかなもの
doing nothing but digging away.
私を眠らすなんてあんたいったいなにもの
What on earth are you to put me to sleep?
さては無本気?
Could you be half-hearted?
僕は勇者ではありません むしろ王が勇者だと思います
I am no hero; rather, I think the king is the hero.
世界平和を取り戻すため...
To restore world peace...
世界平和を取り戻すため
To restore world peace,
奥地の平和を守るため
to protect the peace of the backlands,
最前線に身を閉じ込め
shutting myself away at the front lines,
致死率は目に見えた
the fatality rate is clear as day.
経験値のため お金のために 戦う王様何をみる
For experience, for money, what does the fighting king look at?
この絵も瀕死で絶滅寸前 しんでしまうとはなさけない！
This picture too is on the verge of extinction, it's pathetic to die!
世界平和を取り戻すため あなたの笑顔を守るため
To restore world peace, to protect your smile,
魔法くん 幻想を 独りからからに書き集め
little wizard, writing and gathering illusions all alone,
今日は今日とて死んだふりしてステイする
today pretending to be dead and staying,
本当の勇者を待っている
waiting for the true hero.
体力本願ではありません 知らずが仏よ叶わぬが願い
It's not about physical strength, ignorance is bliss and wishes don't come true.
いろはちゃん、お誕生日に、おめでとう！
Iroha-chan, happy birthday!
おいつものお返し先輩の背景だ、なんかあ、しす...
Ah, that's the returning senior's background, like, a sis...
お祝いできて、すっごく嬉しいよ！
I'm super happy to celebrate with you!
わ、やった！嬉しい。
Wah, yay! I'm so happy.
いろはちゃんは、ミックスを通してすっごく仲良くなったよね！
Iroha-chan, we got so close through the mix, didn't we!
あの時は本当にテトリス、オセロ教えてくれて、ありがとう！
Thank you so much for teaching me Tetris and Othello back then!
また一緒にかき氷とか、オムライスとか食べに行きたいなーなんて！
I'd love to go get shaved ice or omurice with you again sometime!
え、行きたい！食べたい！
Eh, I want to go! I want to eat!
それに、いろはちゃんはいつもある時に美味しい手作りお菓子をくれるんだよねー！
Plus, whenever we meet, Iroha-chan always gives me delicious homemade sweets!
最高のおんな！それが風真いろはなんだよなー！また食べに行かせてください！
The ultimate woman! That's Kazama Iroha! Please let me eat them again!
いつまでもいろはちゃんはぼくのかわいい後輩だよ！
Iroha-chan will always be my cute junior!
本当に大好き！やった！
I really love you! Yay!
これからもいっぱい遊ぼうね！やった！これからもよろしくお願いします！
Let's play lots more together! Yay! Looking forward to more ahead!
お、もうこんな時間だ！ねっこねこホップでそちらへ向かいます！
Oh, look at the time! I'll head over there with Neko-Neko Hop!
ねっこねこホップ！？ねっこねこホップ！？
Neko-Neko Hop!? Neko-Neko Hop!?
痛いことは嫌いですが
I hate things that hurt,
君の手の平は嫌いじゃない
but I don't mind the palm of your hand.
言葉は飴玉みたいに甘く広がって心満たす
Words spread like sweet candy, filling my heart.
ああ 全然分かってない 永遠に言う通り
Ah, you totally don't get it, following orders forever,
風にフェアじゃない
it's not fair at all.
詠う 「何で？」は効いていない もっともっとあの子みたいに
Singing "Why?" has no effect, I gotta be way cuter
可愛くならなくちゃ
than that girl.
愛情は淌明に 傷跡はhow many?
Affection is clear, and how many are the scars?
もう身体墜 痛いのだって分かんなくなる
My body collapses, I can't even tell it hurts anymore.
延命マタタビ 週二ご褒美
Life-extending silvervine, twice-weekly reward.
「もう嫌んなくなった」って 離れられないように
So you can't leave saying "I'm sick of this."
今日だってちゃんと 内緒の毛づくろい
Today too, proper secret grooming.
にゃんにって良い子にするから愛して
I'll be a good girl with a meow, so please love me.
everybody today is rubbing day get it get it this is my courtship any any anytime is fine with me gimme gimme love me my darling
会いたいを間違いなんて皆は言う
Everyone says wanting to meet is a mistake,
取り憑かれているって
that I'm possessed.
ならこの胸でうずく 締め付けるような切なさは何なの
Then what is this tightening anguish buried in my chest?
選ぶ言葉 戸惑い指先
Choosing words, hesitant fingertips.
痛いことは嫌いですが
It hurts, I hate it, but
君の手の平は嫌いじゃない
your palm isn't something I hate.
言葉は飴玉みたいに
Words are like candy drops,
甘く広がって心満たす
spreading sweetly to fill my heart.
ああ 全然わかってない
Ah, you totally don't get it.
永遠に言う通り
Just like you always say,
完全にフェアじゃない
it's completely unfair.
ああ「なんで？」はキテイナイ
Ah, asking "Why?" is out of bounds.
もっともっとあの子みたいに
More and more, like that girl,
カワイイならナチャ
if I'm cute, then...
愛情は霓虹に
Affection to neon,
ショウコンはHow many?
how many for the show-kon?
もうタイダ
Already idle,
痛いのだってわかんなくなる
I won't even know it hurts anymore.
延命マタタビ
Life-extending silver vine,
週にご褒美
a weekly reward.
「もういやなんたって」離れられないように
So that I won't ever want to part ways,
今日だってちゃんと内緒のケツアロイ
today too, keeping our secret safe.
ニャンでいい子にするから愛して
Meow, I'll be a good cat, so love me.
everyday is rubbing day
get it get it this is my courtship
any any any time is fine with me
gimme gimme love my darling
認めていた 臆病な過去
Acknowledging my cowardly past,
わからないままに怖がっていた
I was afraid without even understanding why.
後ろの自分が現実を今に映す
My past self reflects reality into the present.
いくつもの空を描いたここはきっと
This place where I drew countless skies surely
微かな心乱して
disturbs my faint heart.
夢で高く跳んだ躯は
The body that leaped high in my dream
どんな不安纏っても振り払っていく
shakes off any anxiety that clings to it.
眠る小さな想い拡大して
Expanding the small sleeping feelings,
気付く弱い私君がいれば
I realize if you are here, weak me
暗い世界強くいれた
could be strong in a dark world.
長い夢見る心はそう永遠で
My heart dreaming a long dream is forever true,
探していた導く光
searching for the guiding light.
触れればすべて思い出して
If I touch it, I remember everything,
掛け替えのない大切な今をくれる
giving me an irreplaceable, precious present.
目を閉じ世界を知った
I closed my eyes and came to know the world;
それはいつも温かいのに痛くて
even though it's always warm, it hurts so much.
繋ぐ確かな願い重なり合って
Our certain, connecting wishes overlap,
見える迷いは動き始めた
and the visible hesitation begins to move.
君を守りたくて背負う傷は
The wounds I bear because I want to protect you
深い眠りの中漂った
drifted within a deep sleep.
代わらない約束だった
It was an unchanging promise;
二人信じた絆はそう鮮明に
the bond we believed in so vividly
声が届くまで名前を呼んで
calls out your name until my voice reaches you.
出会えた奇跡感じたいもっと
I want to feel the miracle of our meeting even more.
夢で高く跳んだ躯は
The body that leaped high in my dream
どんな不安纏っても振り払っていく
shakes off any anxiety that clings to it.
眠る小さな想い拡大して
Expanding the small sleeping feelings,
気付く弱い私君がいれば
I realize if you are here, weak me
暗い世界強くいれた
could be strong in a dark world.
長い夢見る心はそう永遠で
My heart dreaming a long dream is forever true,
I wanna always be with you
I'll give you everything I have
探し続けてた
Searching for it,
導く光触れれば
the guiding light, if I touch it...
かけがえのない大切な今を
giving me an irreplaceable, precious present.
深い眠りの中ただよった
Drifted within a deep sleep,
変わらない約束だった
It was an unchanging promise.
二人信じた絆はそう鮮明に
The bond we believed in so vividly
声が届くまで名前を呼んで
Calling out your name until my voice reaches you,
出会えた奇跡感じたいもっと
I want to feel the miracle of our meeting even more.
夢で高く跳んだ躯は
The body that leaped high in my dream
どんな不安纏っても振り払っていく
shakes off any anxiety that clings to it.
眠る小さな想い拡大して
Expanding the small sleeping feelings,
気付く弱い私君がいれば
I realize if you are here, weak me
暗い世界強くいれた
could be strong in a dark world.
長い夢見る心はそう永遠で
My heart dreaming a long dream is forever true.
声が届くまで名前を呼んで
Calling out your name until my voice reaches you,
出会えた奇跡感じたいもっと
I want to feel the miracle of our meeting even more.
夢で高く跳んだ躯は
The body that leaped high in my dream
どんな不安纏っても振り払っていく
shakes off any anxiety that clings to it.
眠る小さな想い拡大して
Expanding the small sleeping feelings,
気付く弱い私君がいれば
I realize if you are here, weak me
暗い世界強くいれた
could be strong in a dark world.
長い夢見る心はそう永遠で
My heart dreaming a long dream is forever true,
暖かさに痛くて
even though it's always warm, it hurts so much.
繋ぐ確かな願い重なり合って
Our certain, connecting wishes overlap.
I want to always be with you
I'll give you everything I have
I want to hold you till the end
いろはちゃん！ハッピーニューイヤー！
Iroha-chan! Happy New Year!
あれ？あれ、ちがくね？この子ちがくね？まちがえちゃった！
Huh? Wait, isn't this wrong? This girl is wrong! I made a mistake!
いろは聞いて、今ね、ハッピーニューイヤーじゃなくて、メリークリスマスって
Listen, Iroha, right now, instead of Happy New Year, I was thinking of saying Merry Christmas...
出てこようと思ってて、ハッピーバースデーじゃーんみたいな感じでやろうとしたんだけどさ
and coming out like "Happy Birthday!", but...
ハッピーニューイヤーって言ってしまいました、いろは
I ended up saying Happy New Year, Iroha!
改めまして、いろはちゃん、お誕生日おめでとう！
Once again, Happy Birthday, Iroha-chan!
いろはが焼いてくれたクッキーがさ、もう美味しすぎてさ、バリバリ止まらなかったじゃんか
The cookies Iroha baked were so delicious, I couldn't stop crunching on them!
また食べたいなって思ってるんだけど、また焼いてくれる？
I want to eat them again. Will you bake them for me again?
焼きますとも！
I will!
わあ、嬉しい！ありがとう！
Yay, I'm so happy! Thank you!
あのさ、歌って踊りたいんだよね、一緒にさ、そっちいってもいいかな？
Um, I want to sing and dance together, is it okay if I go over there?
やりますとも！
You bet!
やったー！
Yay!
じゃあ今からそっちに行くいろは
Okay, I'm heading over there right now, Iroha!
待ってろいろは！今ね、今からそっち行くからね！いろは待ってろ！
Wait for me, Iroha! I'm coming over right now! Wait for me, Iroha!
ほらほらまた始まった 得意の自己弁護言い訳 「でもね」「だって」
Look, it started again, your self-defense excuses: "But you see...", "Because..."
ほらほらまた始まった ごめん！からのはkissのパターンって感じ？ 安易
Look, it started again, a "Sorry!" followed by a kiss pattern? So easy.
“いつかアタシだけ”そんな夢見たこともあったけど
"Someday only me"—I used to dream of that, but...
寂しい時だけ電話して もううざいわ！
You only call when you're lonely, it's so annoying!
全然アタシに興味ないじゃん キミが好きなのは自分でしょう（Yeah!）
You're not interested in me at all! You only love yourself, don't you? (Yeah!)
やっぱりアタシに興味ないじゃん その話もう聞き飽きたわ
As I thought, you're not interested in me. I'm sick of hearing that story.
そもそもだいたいアタシに興味ないじゃん そーやってまた誤魔化して…（もう！）
Above all, you're not interested in me at all. Always dodging it like that... (Geez!)
be my boy わがまま過ぎるbaby 抱きしめてよね！
Be my boy, you selfish baby, hold me tight!
ホントキミはしょうもないな 甘いアタシ「しょうがないな」
You really are hopeless, and soft-hearted me says "It can't be helped."
泣いたって行かないでって言ったって変わりゃしないや！
Even if I cry and tell you not to go, nothing ever changes!
もう少しだけなら踊ってもいいかもな とろけてとろけてイキたいの
Maybe I could dance a little longer, melting away into bliss.
どんなアピールも意味ないし気づいてくれないけど アタシが寂しい時だけは 逢いにきて！
No appeal means anything and you never notice, but when I'm lonely, come see me!
全然アタシに興味ないじゃん どこがダメなの？教えてよ（Yeah!）
You're not interested in me at all! What's wrong with me? Tell me! (Yeah!)
やっぱりアタシに興味ないじゃん 携帯ばかりいじってさ
As I thought, you're not interested in me, just fiddling with your phone.
そもそもだいたいアタシに興味ないじゃん 少しぐらい期待させ得て（もう…）
Above all, you're not interested in me at all. Give me at least a little hope... (Geez...)
lonely girl 独りじめしてよbaby 振り回さないで！
Lonely girl, keep me all to yourself, baby, don't push me around!
ねぇ？ maybe melty? ワン・ツー shall we dance? 踊りましょう
Hey? Maybe melty? One, two, shall we dance? Let's dance!
はやく手と手繋いで最後にひとつだけ 溺れるくらい愛してよ
Hurry and take my hand, just one last thing: love me until I drown in it.
全然アタシに興味ないじゃん キミが好きなのは自分でしょう（Yeah!）
You're not interested in me at all! You only love yourself, don't you? (Yeah!)
やっぱりアタシに興味ないじゃん その話もう聞き飽きたわ
As I thought, you're not interested in me. I'm sick of hearing that story.
そもそもだいたいアタシに興味ないじゃん そーやってまた誤魔化して…（もう！）
Above all, you're not interested in me at all. Always dodging it like that... (Geez!)
Get the last dance 覚悟はできているの？ 気まぐれメルシィ …お味はいかが？
Get the last dance, are you ready? Kimagure Mercy... how does it taste?
ほらほらまた始まった 得意の自己弁護言い訳
Look, it started again, your self-defense excuses.
「でもね」「だって」 ほらほらまた始まった
"But you see...", "Because..." Look, it started again.
ごめん！からのはkissのパターンって感じ？ 安易
A "Sorry!" followed by a kiss pattern? So easy.
“いつかアタシだけ”そんな夢見たこともあったけど
"Someday only me"—I used to dream of that, but...
寂しい時だけ電話して もううざいわ！
You only call when you're lonely, it's so annoying!
全然アタシに興味ないじゃん キミが好きなのは自分でしょう（Yeah!）
You're not interested in me at all! You only love yourself, don't you? (Yeah!)
やっぱりアタシに興味ないじゃん その話もう聞き飽きたわ
As I thought, you're not interested in me. I'm sick of hearing that story.
そもそもだいたいアタシに興味ないじゃん そーやってまた誤魔化して…（もう！）
Above all, you're not interested in me at all. Always dodging it like that... (Geez!)
be my boy わがまま過ぎるbaby 抱きしめてよね！
Be my boy, you selfish baby, hold me tight!
ホントキミはしょうもないな 甘いアタシ「しょうがないな」
You really are hopeless, and soft-hearted me says "It can't be helped."
泣いたって行かないでって言ったって変わりゃしないや！
Even if I cry and tell you not to go, nothing ever changes!
もう少しだけなら踊ってもいいかもな とろけてとろけてイキたいの
Maybe I could dance a little longer, melting away into bliss.
どんなアピールも意味ないし気づいてくれないけど アタシが寂しい時だけは 逢いにきて！
No appeal means anything and you never notice, but when I'm lonely, come see me!
全然アタシに興味ないじゃん どこがダメなの？教えてよ（Yeah!）
You're not interested in me at all! What's wrong with me? Tell me! (Yeah!)
やっぱりアタシに興味ないじゃん 携帯ばかりいじってさ
As I thought, you're not interested in me, just fiddling with your phone.
そもそもだいたいアタシに興味ないじゃん 少しぐらい期待させ得て（もう…）
Above all, you're not interested in me at all. Give me at least a little hope... (Geez...)
lonely girl 独りじめしてよbaby 振り回さないで！
Lonely girl, keep me all to yourself, baby, don't push me around!
気まぐれメルシィ おしまいはいかが？
Kimagure Mercy, how is the ending?
しまーす！
Let's do this!
ソロライブに、あおぞら……すばー！
For the solo live, Ao... Suba!
いろはの、お誕生日おめでとう！
Iroha, happy birthday!
おめでとうおめでとうおめでとうおめでとうおめでとうおめでとう！
Congratulations, congratulations, congratulations!
ねー、今日はいろはの応援に駆けつけましたー！
You know, today I rushed over to cheer for Iroha!
ありがとうございます！元気ですかね。
Thank you so much! I wonder how she's doing.
いや、やっぱりね、いろはのと言えばね、はい。
Well, speaking of Iroha, yeah.
最初は、だ、大丈夫かなこの子、なんかすごいフワフワしてる。
At first, like, "Is this girl okay? She's so fluffy."
大丈夫かジャングルキング？そんなだ、大丈夫？みたいな感じだったんですけど。
"Is Jungle King okay? Is she really okay?" It felt like that.
もちろんね、いまやもうすごく立派になってというような感じで。
Of course, now she has become so magnificent and all.
なんかいろはのはですね、本当にまっすぐで頑張り屋さんなのでね、これからもね、そのままでの素敵ないろはのでいてください。
Iroha is really straightforward and a hard worker, so please continue to be the wonderful Iroha you are.
そうですね、いろはのにとってこの1年が素敵な1年になりますように、陰ながら応援しております！
Hoping this year will be a wonderful year for Iroha, I'm supporting her from the shadows!
ありがとうございます！
Thank you very much!
さあ、ではね、ちょっとね、もうちょっとね、近くでね、いろはのを応援したいと、思いましてね、応援しにこちらからそちらに向かいます！
I thought I'd get a bit closer to cheer for Iroha, so I'm heading over there from here!
おっしゃあ！それでは、ワープするぞー！
All right! Here we go, warping!
ワープ！せーの、かおーーーお！
Warp! Ready, set, Kaooo!
神のまにまに / 作詞・作曲：れるりり
Kamisama no Manimani / Lyrics & Music: rerulili
思い通りにいかないことだらけ
Full of things that don't go as expected,
どうしようもなく自己嫌悪
filled with helpless self-loathing.
宵々の痛みや苦しみから 逃げ込める場所を探してる
Searching for a place to escape the nightly pain and sorrow.
一寸の闇の隙間に引っ込んで
Hiding away in a tiny gap of darkness,
月も太陽も無視して眠ろう
ignoring both moon and sun, I'll just sleep.
生まれてきたことの意味なんて 知らない 分かんないよ
I don't know the meaning of being born, I just don't get it at all!
でもそんなふうに思えるってこと
But being able to feel that way—
それは君がもっともっと素敵になれる力があるって教えてるんだよ
it tells us you have the power to become so much more wonderful!
そうさ 神のまにまに オーセのままに
That's right, at the god's whim, just as we are,
誰だって地球を愛してる
everyone loves this earth.
飲むや歌いや とんちゃん騒ぎ 霊(あやかし)そんなのもいいね
Drinking, singing, making a ruckus—spirits and such are nice too.
そうさ 北も南も 右も左も なんやかんや地球を愛してる
That's right, north and south, right and left—somehow or other, we love the earth!
悩むこともあるけど 歩いてゆける まだまだ先は長いのさ
There are things to worry about, but we can keep walking; there's still a long way ahead.
ただ正しい人でいたいだけ きっと誰もがそれを望んでいるけど
Just wanting to be a righteous person—surely everyone wishes for that, but
宵々の心の内側に 苦しめられる毎日さ
every day we are tormented deep within our nightly hearts.
僕が生まれてきたこと 奇跡と言えば聞こえはいいけど
My being born—calling it a miracle sounds nice,
それは物理法則(ぜんいん)に過ぎなくて やっぱ意味なんてないじゃん
but it's nothing more than physical laws, so after all, there's no real meaning.
えもっと例えば君にいじわるをする 野良猫ならそれは君にとってとっても素敵な人だって教えてるんだよ
And if someone teases you like a stray cat, it's teaching you that they're actually a wonderful person to you!
そうさ 神のまにまに オーセのままに 誰だって地球を愛してる
That's right, at the god's whim, just as we are, everyone loves this earth.
僕が笑って 君も笑えば 許されないことなんてないよ
If I laugh and you laugh, there's nothing that cannot be forgiven.
そうさ どこまでも 恋しくなるべき そんなふうに地球を回ってる
That's right, going on and on, how we should yearn—that's how the earth spins.
そうさ どこまでも 歩いて行こう まだまだ続きは長いさ
That's right, let's keep walking on and on, there's still a long way to go.
本当に大事なものなんて 悪足掻きくだらないことの中にあるよ
Truly important things are found within petty, foolish struggles.
時にはみんなでバカ騒ぎ 裸踊りで
Sometimes everyone makes a fool of themselves dancing naked.
おお笑い!
Big laugh!
そうさ 神のまにまに オーセのままに もっともっと自分を愛せるよ 鏡を見てごらんよ
That's right, at the god's whim, just as we are, you can love yourself even more—look in the mirror!
もう分かるでしょ みんなを照らす光さ
You already know, right? You're the light that illuminates everyone.
そうさ 神のまにまに みんなありがとう やっぱ
That's right, at the god's whim, thank you everyone, after all!
思い通りにいかないことばかりどうしようもなく自己嫌悪
I feel hopelessly self-loathing when things don't go my way,
八百万の痛みや悲しみから逃れ込める場所を探している
searching for a place to escape countless pains and sorrows.
いっそ岩の隙間に引きこもって月も太陽も無視して眠ろう
I might as well hide in a rock crevice and sleep, ignoring moon and sun.
生まれてきたことの意味なんて知らない 分かんないよ
I don't know the meaning of being born, I just don't get it.
でもそんな風に思えることそれは 君がもっともっと素敵になれる力があるって教えてるんだよ
But the fact that you can think that way proves you have the power to grow even more wonderful.
そうさ 神のまにまに 仰せのままに 誰だって地球を愛している
That's right, as gods will, as fate commands, everyone loves this earth!
飲めや歌えや どんちゃん騒ぎ たまにそんなのもいいね
Drink and sing, make a ruckus—such nights are fine once in a while.
そうさ 北も南も 右も左も なんかかんか地球を愛している
That's right, north and south, right and left, somehow we all love the earth.
泥んこだけど歩いていける まだまだ先は長いさ
We can keep walking even if we're muddy; the road ahead is still long.
そうさ 神のまにまに みんなありがとう やっぱり地球を愛している
That's right, as gods will, thank you everyone, we truly love this earth!
花を咲かせよう 大きな花を 天まで届くくらいの
Let's make flowers bloom, massive flowers reaching up to the heavens!
悲しみの海に沈んだ私
I've sunk deep into the sea of sadness,
目を開けるのも億劫
where even opening my eyes is too much effort.
このままどこまでをも堕ちて行き 誰にも見つけられないのかな
Will I keep falling endlessly like this, unable to be found by anyone?
どこへ向かい 何をすれば?
Where should I head, what should I do?
ふと射し込む一筋の光 手を伸ばせば届きそうだけど
A sudden ray of light shines through—if I reach out, it seems within reach,
波にさらわれて見失った
but the waves carried it away and I lost it.
あれは一体なんだったのかな
What in the world was that?
温かくて眩しかったな
It was so warm and dazzling.
無意識のカウンターイルミネーション 嘘つきは誰?
Unconscious counter-illumination, who is the liar?
深海少女 まだまだ沈む
Deep sea girl, sinking further down,
暗闇の彼方へ閉じこもる
shutting herself away in the distant darkness.
深海少女 だけど知りたい 心惹かれるあの人を見つけたから
Deep sea girl, yet she wants to know, for she found someone who captivates her heart.
昼も夜もなかったこの場所
This place had neither day nor night,
なのに眠れない夜は続く
yet the sleepless nights go on.
自由の羽大きく広げて 泳ぐあなたは綺麗でした
You looked so beautiful swimming with your freedom wings spread wide.
そしてまた光は降り注ぐ 見とれていたらし目が合った
And then light pours down once more—as I gazed entranced, our eyes met.
気付いてこっちを振り返るあなたに 嘘つきな私…
When you noticed and turned toward me, I lied to you...
深海少女 わざわざ沈む 暗闇のさなかに赤い頬
Deep sea girl, purposely sinking down, red cheeks amidst the darkness.
深海少女 ハダカの心を見せる勇気 黒い海がまだ許さない
Deep sea girl, still lacking the courage to bare her heart; the black ocean won't allow it yet.
こんなに服は汚れてしまって 笑顔も醜くゆがんでいった
My clothes have grown so soiled, and my smile distorted so hatefully.
誰にも合わせる顔なんてないの もう放っておいてよ!
I have no face to show anyone anymore—just leave me be!
声にならない気持ちが溢れてとけた 次の瞬間、君が突然姿を消した
Unspoken feelings overflowed and dissolved; the next moment, you suddenly vanished.
心配性の彼女は焦る 闇が彼を隠しひとりきり
Filled with anxiety, she panics as the shadows hide him away, leaving her all alone.
限界少女 その手を伸ばす 「ほらね、君も素敵な色を隠してた」
Reaching her limit, she stretches out her hand: "See? You were hiding a wonderful color too."
深海少女 腕を引かれる 歌う祝福のマリスノーツ
Deep sea girl, her arm is pulled—the blessing of Maris Stella sings out.
次の瞬間 君が突然 姿を消した… 消した
In the blink of an eye, you suddenly vanished... vanished.
心配性の彼女は焦る 闇が彼を隠し…
Filled with anxiety, she panics as the shadows hide him away...
限界少女 その手を伸ばす ほらね 君も素敵な色を隠してたんだ
Reaching her limit, she stretches out her hand: "See? You were hiding a wonderful color too."
深海少女 腕を引かれる 歌う祝福のマリンスノウ
Deep sea girl, her arm is pulled—the blessing of Marine Snow sings out.
深海少女 もっと知りたい 心惹かれるあの人を見つけたから
Deep sea girl, she wants to know more, for she found the person who captivates her heart.
この海を出て 今飛び立つのだ
Leaving this sea, now she will take flight!
いろはちゃん、お誕生日おめでとう！
Iroha-chan, happy birthday!
はすきー、ハッピーバースデー！ありがとう！
Hazuki— Happy Birthday! Thank you so much!
どうも、AZKiです。
Hello, I'm AZKi.
えー、いろはちゃんとは、今年もあずいろでグッズを一緒に買いに行ったり…
Uh, Iroha-chan and I went shopping for Azuiro goods together this year...
個人的に、串カツ屋さんに行ったり…
And went to kushikatsu restaurants personally...
いつも仲良くしてくれて、ありがとう！
Thank you for always being such a good friend!
ライブの時に歌った桜ロックも
The Sakura Rock we sang at the live,
二人、歌声が合っていたし？
did you two sound good together?
っていたし？
Right?
なんと、この後も一緒に歌っちゃう？歌っちゃうのか！
And what, we're gonna sing together again after this?
ということで、これからもぜひあずいろよろしくお願いします！
So from here on too, please look forward to it, Iroha.
これからもよろしくお願いします。
Please look forward to it.
ということで、今からワープして、そちらに向かいます！
So, right now we'll warp and head to our destination!
いってらっしゃーい！
See you there!
可愛いな。
So cute.
誰よりも近くにいた その声は聴こえなくて
Closer to me than anyone else, I couldn't hear that voice.
刻み続けていた時の中で やっと君に逢えたから
Within the ticking time, I was finally able to meet you.
sister's noise 探し続ける 彷徨う心の場所を
sister's noise, continuing to search for a wandering heart's place.
重ね合った この想いは誰にも壊せないから...！
These overlapping feelings cannot be destroyed by anyone...
街は密やかに 君を隠していた
The streets were quietly hiding you away.
辿り着いた場所を 蘇るあの記憶
The place I arrived at revives those memories.
繰り返されていた 真実は遠く
It was repeating, the truth is far away.
君のその痛み 気づけないまま
Without even realizing your pain.
あの日誓ったその夢が 私を切り裂いても
Even if the dream I wished upon that day tears me apart,
何よりも大切な 希望だけ信じ貫いて
I will keep believing in the hope that is more precious than anything.
自分らしく生きること 何よりも伝えたくて
I want to convey living true to myself more than anything,
生まれ続く哀しみの痛み その意味を刻むなら
if I'm to carve out the meaning of the sorrowful pain that keeps being born.
sister's noise いま届けるよ 涙さえ能力(チカラ)にして
sister's noise, deliver it now, turning even tears into power.
繋がり合う 強さだけが全てを打ち抜いていく
Connected strengths are what cut through everything.
夕暮れの放課後 いつもの街並み
After-school in the dusk, the usual streetscape.
ふと見上げた空想い出す 優しさを
I remember the sky I casually looked up at, and its kindness.
君の眼差しが 気づかせてくれた
Your gaze made me realize
弱さ認める 勇気の強さを
the strength in the courage to admit my weakness.
温かな君のその手が 私を導いていく
Your warm hand guides me on.
何よりも守りたい 希望が闇を貫くから
Because the hope I want to protect more than anything pierces through the darkness.
抱きしめた熱い想い この世界を照らすから
The warm feelings I held close will illuminate this world.
走り続け探し続けていた 君の夢が動き出す
Continuing to run and search, your dream starts to move.
sister's noise 響きはじめる 高らかな生命の意味
sister's noise, the sound begins to echo, the grand meaning of life.
理解ってるよ かけがえない絆は壊せないこと
I understand, irreplaceable bonds cannot be broken.
自分らしく生きること 何よりも伝えたくて
I want to convey living true to myself more than anything,
生まれ続く哀しみの痛み その意味を刻むなら
if I'm to carve out the meaning of the sorrowful pain that keeps being born.
誰よりも近くにいた その声は聴こえなくて
Closer to me than anyone else, I couldn't hear that voice.
刻み続けていた時の中で やっと君に逢えたから
Within the ticking time, I was finally able to meet you.
sister's noise 探し続ける 彷徨う 心 の 場所 を
sister's noise, continuing to search for a wandering heart's place.
感じ合った 同じ笑顔 必ず守ってみせる
Feeling each other, I will surely protect that same smile.
もう誰にも壊せないから...！
Because it won't be broken by anyone ever again...!
街は密やかに 君を隠していた
The town was quietly hiding you away.
辿り着いた場所を 蘇るあの記憶
The place I arrived at revives those memories.
繰り返されていた 真実は遠く
It was repeating, the truth is far away.
君のその痛み 気づけないまま
Without even realizing your pain.
あの日誓ったその夢が 私を切り裂いても
Even if the dream I wished upon that day tears me apart,
何よりも大切な 希望だけ信じ貫いて
I will keep believing in the hope that is more precious than anything.
自分らしく生きること 何よりも伝えたくて
I want to convey living true to myself more than anything,
生まれ続く哀しみの痛み その意味を刻むなら
if I'm to carve out the meaning of the sorrowful pain that keeps being born.
sister's noise いま届けるよ 涙さえ力にして
sister's noise, deliver it now, turning even tears into power.
繋がり合う 強さだけが全てを打ち抜いていく
Connected strengths are what cut through everything.
自分らしく生きること 何よりも伝えたくて
I want to convey living true to myself more than anything,
生まれ続く哀しみの痛み その意味を刻むなら
if I'm to carve out the meaning of the sorrowful pain that keeps being born.
誰よりも近くにいた その声は聴こえなくて
Closer to me than anyone else, I couldn't hear that voice.
刻み続けていた時の中で やっと君に逢えたから
Within the ticking time, I was finally able to meet you.
sister's noise 探し続ける 彷徨う心の場所を
sister's noise, continuing to search for a wandering heart's place.
重ね合った この想いは誰にも壊せないから...！
These overlapping feelings cannot be destroyed by anyone...
街は密やかに 君を隠していた
The town was quietly hiding you away.
辿り着いた場所を 蘇るあの記憶
The place I arrived at revives those memories.
同じ笑顔 必ず守ってみせる
I will always show you the exact same smile.
もう誰にも壊せないから...！
Because it won't be broken by anyone ever again...!
はい、というわけで
And that's that!
これ、
This...
盛りだくさんの歌とダンスをお届けさせていただきましたでござる！
We've brought you a packed lineup of songs and dances!
そしてね、あの新衣装のときにお着替えしてちょっと紹介するタイミングなかったんですけど、
And you know, I didn't have a chance to introduce it when I changed into my new outfit,
じゃじゃーーん！ブルベ衣装でござる！
ta-da! It's my cool-toned outfit!
なんかんだね、自分の配信で切るのは初めてのこの衣装、エキスパ？
Somehow, this is the first time I'm wearing this outfit on my own stream. Expert...?
ブリエでござるな、どうですか？
Bright, right? How is it?
そしてなんと今回はですね、さっきまでスパッツ穿いてたんですけど、今初めてスカート穿いてみました！
And what's more, this time, I was wearing leggings until just now, but for the first time, I tried wearing a skirt!
ちょっとスースーするでござるな。あんま慣れないんですけど、どうですか？どうですか？
It feels a little breezy. I'm not really used to it, but how do you like it? How is it?
スカートもいいでござるな！このあとはね、せっかくなんでこのスカートで歌って踊っていきたいと思います！
The skirt is nice too! Since we have the chance, I'd like to sing and dance in this skirt next!
いや可愛いですよね！そしてね、みんなとの難曲も聴いて、見ていただいたと思うんですが、
It's so cute, right? And I think you all listened to and watched the difficult song together with me,
ね、ステージもいい感じで、気づいた人いるかな？
right? The stage looks great, and I wonder if anyone noticed?
この中にですね、なんとポコベェ隠れてるんですけど、気づいた大将、いますかーー？
Hidden right inside here is actually Pokobee! Is there any general who noticed?
いるか？今コメント見てるんだけど、いる？
Is there? I'm looking at the comments now. Is there?
スカートも可愛い、ありがとう！新⑨、え、いるでござるか？
"The skirt is cute too, thank you!" Chapter 9? Huh, is Pokobee here?
あ、いない？いや、いるんだな、実はポコベェが。
Ah, not here? No, Pokobee is actually here.
ポコベェがね、あのへんにね、ちょっと待ってね、あのへんに、あれ？なんか、なんかポコベェ、なんか様子がおかしいでござるな。
Pokobee is... around there, wait, around there, huh? Pokobee, something looks weird with Pokobee.
あれ？
Huh?
ポコベェ？
Pokobee?
うわ、ポコベェ！
Whoa, Pokobee!
もう、いつも何かが起きるポコベェに、うわ！
Seriously, something always happens to Pokobee! Whoa!
ポコベェ、お前動けるようになったのか？
Pokobee, were you able to move?
え、ポコベェ？え、ポコベェ？ポコベェ！
Eh, Pokobee? Eh, Pokobee? Pokobee!
そうだね、足遅いからドローン乗んなきゃいつもいけないんだよね。
That's right, since your legs are slow, you always have to ride a drone.
そうだよね。え、ポコベェ？
That's right. Eh, Pokobee?
え、動いてるよね？
Eh, it's moving, right?
あ、あ、あ、みんなポコベェが来るぞ！
Ah, ah, ah, everyone, Pokobee is coming!
ポコベェ！ポコベェ！ポコベェ！ポコベェ！
Pokobee! Pokobee! Pokobee! Pokobee!
いや、ポコベェ！こっち見て！え、めっちゃこっち来るじゃん！
Hey, Pokobee! Look this way! Eh, it's coming right at me!
え、ポコベェ、お前動けるようになったんか？
Eh, Pokobee, did you become able to move?
え？あ、来る！あ、くねくねする、ポコベェ！
Eh? Ah, it's coming! Ah, it's wriggling, Pokobee!
ポコベェーー！
Poko-beee!
ということで、まさかのですね、ポコベェが来てくれましたーー！
And so, incredibly, Pokobee has come to join us!
ポコベェーー！えーー！
Pokobee! Yay!
え、自由に動けるようになったでござるか、ポコベェ？
Eh, you became able to move freely, Pokobee?
よかったね！
I'm so glad!
え、せっかくだからじゃあ一緒にちょっと写真でもいかがですか、ポコベェさん？
Eh, since we have the chance, how about taking a picture together, Pokobee-san?
え、え？
Eh, eh?
いや、まさか最後にゲストとして動けるようになったポコベェが来てくれるとは。いぇーーい！ポコベェ！
Man, I never expected Pokobee to come as a guest who can finally move around. Yay! Pokobee!
え、せーの、ほっ！せーの、ほっ！せーの、ほっ！
Eh, ready, heave! Ready, heave! Ready, heave!
え、ポコベェ、すごいね！動けるようになったね！
Eh, Pokobee, amazing! You can move now!
みんな、めっ、みんな、でっかって言われてるよ、ポコベェ。でかっ、て。
Everyone, ev-, everyone is saying you're huge, Pokobee. "Huge," they say.
あ、でかい？あ、でかくない？
Ah, huge? Ah, not huge?
あ、可愛いって、ポコベェ。
Ah, "so cute," Pokobee.
ああ、可愛いそうだよね、可愛い、でござるよね。
Ah, that's right, so cute, isn't it cute.
みんなのポコベェ、拍手！可愛いー！あ、可愛いね、ポコベェ。
Everyone's Pokobee, applause! So cute! Ah, so cute, Pokobee.
ね、せっかくね、今日ポコベェとね、ついにステージに立てたということで、え、何気に動き、ポコベェ動けるようになったの初めてでござるよな？
You know, since today we finally stood on stage together with Pokobee, this is actually the first time Pokobee has been able to move around, right?
そうだよね、嬉しいよね！
That's right, I'm so happy!
そうだよね。じゃあ、せっかく来たので、ポコベェ、今回初一緒に踊っちゃいますか？
That's right. Well then, since you came, Pokobee, shall we dance together for the first time?
踊りますか？
Shall we dance?
おお！ということで、じゃあ次の曲はですね、ポコベェと一緒に踊って、彼女が歌いたいとーーもーーいーーまぁーーす！
Oh! And so, for the next song, I think Pokobee and I will dance and she wants to singー!
よし！というわけで、ちょっとポコベェがね、準備中でございます。ポコベェ、準備はいいでござるか？
Alright! And so, Pokobee is currently getting ready. Pokobee, are you ready?
お、良さそうなので、それでは一緒に頑張っていきたいと思います！
Oh, looks good, so let's do our best together!
それでは、聞いてください。何が悪い。
Now then, please listen. Nani ga Warui (What's Wrong).
鳴り止まなくてなにが悪い
What's wrong with not letting my sound die down?
青春でなにが悪い
What's wrong with being young?
ねえどうして止まらない止められない見つむか
Hey, why doesn't it stop? The rhythm I can't stop
身体の中響いているイヤホンから
keeps reverberating through my body from my earphones.
流れるメロディだけが私を私でいさせてくれた
The melody playing is the only thing that lets me be who I am.
赤色に染まる空私の心は何色なんだろう教えて
The sky is tinged in red, but what color is my soul? Please tell me.
私は何処へ向かえばいい？ずっと探していた
Where should I go? I've always been searching
大切な何かを (ほら！) いつか失くして
for something precious (Hola!) before losing it
しまうものばかりなら強くきざいでおこう (いま！)
someday, let's engrave it as deep as we can (Now!)
みじめな夜もばか笑いもあの日そのあとが言えなかった日も
My most pathetic nights and cackling laughter, and days when I couldn't say more than "you know..."
鳴り止まなくてなにが悪い青春でなにが悪い
What's wrong with not letting my sound die down? What's wrong with being young?
もっとあとが言えなかった日も もう
Even on days when I couldn't say more,
なりやまなくって何が悪い
What's wrong with it echoing endlessly?
青春で何が悪い
What's wrong with youth?
ネトストして踏んでみたい 踏めない未来から
Wanting to online stalk and step into a future I can't reach,
今日も僕を迷わせてる みんなは知らないあのバンドの曲
today too, that band's song that nobody knows makes me lost.
君にだけ聞かせたいんだ 何もかもが悲しいほど
I want to make only you listen to it, as if everything is so sad,
綺麗で満点寂しくなったよ
it became so beautifully perfect and lonely.
机の上にはない僕らの後悔 ずっと隠してた
Our regrets not found on the desk, I kept hiding them,
最適な言葉を
looking for the optimal words...
ダイマギャクなんだ 何が悪い
It's completely the opposite, what's wrong with that?
たとえて人と違う夢描くこと 君と喧嘩したこと
For instance, dreaming a dream different from others, getting into a fight with you,
すべて最高のプレゼント
all of it is the best present.
大人になった僕へのプレゼント
A present to myself who has grown up.
ねぇ、そう信じてるんだ 何が悪い
Hey, I believe that, what's wrong with that?
綺麗で満点寂しくなったよ
It became so beautifully perfect and lonely.
教えて僕員はどこへ向かえばいい
Tell me, where should I head?
心の中の答えは
The answer inside my heart...
心臓がうるさく僕に伝える
My heartbeat loudly tells me,
急ぎ足ですぐ其処へ
hurry on to right over there.
理不尽な夜もバカじゃないもんね
Even unreasonable nights aren't foolish, right?
そうあとが言えなかった日の枝を
Yes, the branch of the day when I couldn't say the rest...
なりやまなくって何が悪い
What's wrong with it echoing endlessly?
青春で何が悪い
What's wrong with youth?
はい、ということでですね、
Yes, so,
ぽこべと一緒になにが悪い踊らせていただきました！
PokoBE and I danced to "Nani ga Warui"!
ぽこべ、ありがとーー！
PokoBE, thank you~~!
いやー、楽しかった！
Man, that was fun!
ぽこべ！
PokoBE!
いや、よかった！
Man, that was great!
何気にこういう機械なかったから、風真と一緒に踊れて楽しかったでござる！
We didn't have many chances like this casually, so I was happy to dance with Kazama!
今日は来てくれてありがとう、ぽこべ！
Thank you for coming today, PokoBE!
そして、どうやら、なんかこの生誕ライブトレンドが2位みたいで、ありがとうございます！
And, it seems like this birthday live trended at #2, thank you!
日曜のこの時間まで毎回決まったのトレンドがあるんですけど、そのトレンドにもね、皆さんのいっぱい積み合ってくれて、ありがとうございます！
Up to this time on Sunday, there's always a fixed trend, but even for that trend, everyone piled up so much, thank you!
後でね、風真もライブ終わったらゆっくりね、みんなでの感想を見させてもらうので、
Later, once Kazama's live is over, I'll leisurely read everyone's impressions,
まだまだいっぱいツイートよろしくお願いします！
so please keep tweeting a lot!
さて、ぽこべと一緒に踊って楽しかったね！
Now, dancing with PokoBE was fun!
そろそろ1回戻んないとな、ぽこべ！
It's about time you head back once, PokoBE!
そうだよね！じゃあみんなにいっぱいバイバイってして！
That's right! Then say bye-bye to everyone a lot!
バイバーイ！あ、かわいいねぽこべ！
Bye-bye! Ah, cute, PokoBE!
ありがとう！
Thank you!
じゃあさっきにね、道場に戻ってゆっくりしててくださいね！
Then as before, please go back to the dojo and take it easy!
はーい、ぽこべありがとねー！
Alright, thanks PokoBE!
お、そ、そういう消え方なんだ！
Oh, so, that's how you disappear!
はあ、ぽこべ、そういう消え方するんだ。ちょ、ドロン、ドロンだったね今完全に。
Ha, PokoBE, you disappear like that. Wait, it was totally "doron, doron" just now.
ぽこべ忍者なのかな？え、違うよ風真侍だけどね。
Is PokoBE a ninja? Ah, no, Kazama's a samurai though.
と言うわけで楽しい時間はあっという間でござるな！
That being said, fun times fly by in a flash!
なんと次の曲がね、そのすみません、あの最後の曲になってしまうんでござるが、
And the next song is... sorry, it's going to be the last song,
え、今来たばっかりー！と、その前に、やっぱりやりますよ！はい、告知です！
but "Ah, we just got here!" And before that, of course we're doing it! Yes, it's an announcement!
それでは行きますよ！せーの、どどん！
Here we go! Ready, set, bam!
まずグッズ出てます！やったー！
First, the merch is out! Yay!
風真いろは誕生日記念2023グッズ！はい、今回もですね、可愛いイラストと共に可愛いグッズをたくさんご用意させていただきました！
Kazama Iroha Birthday Commemoration 2023 Goods! Yes, this time too, we've prepared lots of cute goods along with cute illustrations!
ありがとうございます！それでは順番にご紹介していきましょう！
Thank you! Now let's introduce them in order!
はい、じゃあ最初は、こちら！絵皿！
Yes, so first, this one! Illustrated plate!
いやー、可愛いめでござるよな！
Man, it's so cute!
今回ですね、えっと、リズ先生にイラストをお願いさせていただきました。可愛い！
This time, um, we asked Liz-sensei to do the illustration. Cute!
はーい、ありがとうございます。
Hi, thank you so much.
風真のね、あの、
Kazama's...
ファンの皆さん、
Fans and
劔さんたちはよく風真のレシピを模倣してクッキーとか作ってくださっている
Tsurugi-san often recreate Kazama's recipes to make cookies and things,
と思うので、それを食べるのに使っていただいたり、
so I thought you could use this plate to eat them,
飾ってもね、かわいいと思うので、
and it's super cute to display too!
ぜひね、いろんな用途でお皿使ってください！
So please use these plates for various things!
風真も使います！
I'll use them too!
これにガトーショコラを置くんだ、風真。
I'm gonna put gateau chocolat on this.
はい、じゃあ次いきますね、こちらです。
Okay, moving on to the next one, here it is.
はい、そして同じイラストでコースターをご用意させていただきました！
And with the same illustration, we have a coaster!
なんかあの、お皿のときってコースターって…
It's like, when you have a plate, a coaster...
そうなんです、この後もどんどん見ていただきますが、
That's right, we'll be showing more after this, but
みなとの今回はですね、日常生活で一緒に使っていただけるようなものをたくさん用意しております。
this time we've prepared lots of items you can use together in daily life.
コースターもですね、かわいいデザインになっておりますので、ぜひ学校職場…
The coaster also has a cute design, so please use it at school, work,
使えるところでね、おうちでもどんどん使っていただけると嬉しいです！
or wherever you can, even at home!
それでは次！
Now, onto the next!
次はですね、さまずる先生にイラストを描いていただきました、こちらビッグタオルでございまーす！
Next is the big towel illustrated by Samateru-sensei! Here it is!
かわいい！
How cute!
もうね、ちょっと、お風呂上がり？
After a bath?
もう飾れる、なんでも用途あり、
You can display it, use it for anything,
本当にね、みなとの生活に役立てていただければと思います。
I really hope it can be useful in everyone's daily lives.
いや、風真もいっぱい使うぞ、ありがとうございます。
Yep, Kazama's gonna use it a lot too, thank you.
そしてみなとのこのイラスト、ちょっと覚えておいてね。
And please remember this illustration.
このイラスト、よく目に焼き付けといてくださいね。
Burn this illustration into your eyes.
はいじゃあ次いきます。
Okay, moving on.
はい、次がタンブラーです。
Next is the tumbler.
なんとね、蓋付きでございます。あの、
It even comes with a lid, you know. Um,
あの水はこぼさない仕様になっておりますので、
it's designed so water won't spill,
コースターと合わせてね、ぜひ使っていただけるととってもとっても嬉しいです！
so I'd be so happy if you use it with the coaster!
ぜひたくさん使ってください。こちらもポコベージュデザインでーす。
Please use it a lot. This also has the Poco Beige design.
願いまーす。そしてそして今回も記念ボイス、あります。
Please look forward to it. And, and, we also have commemorative voice packs!
それでは記念ボイスがうーこっち…大変お待たせしました！
Now, for the voice packs, um, here... Sorry to keep you waiting!
風真いろはのシステムボイス12種ということで、以前からですね、
Kazama Iroha's System Voice 12-pack! Since before,
いろはちゃんのシステムボイス欲しいなっていうことで声をいただいておりました。
people have been saying they wanted my system voice.
今回ですね、12種類頑張って、
So this time I worked hard on 12 types,
パソコンのシステムボイス取らせていただきました！
and got to record PC system voices!
いや、なんかね、ユニークで楽しいシステムボイスがいっぱい揃っておりますので
There are lots of unique and fun system voices gathered here,
ぜひね、みなとのパソコンにインストールして、あの毎日の生活の彩りにしていただければと思います。
so I hope you'll install them on your PCs to brighten up your daily lives.
はい、そしてフルセットがこのようになっております。
And here is how the full set looks.
はーい、こんな感じです。そしてフルセット購入特典でですね、
Ta-da! And as a full set purchase bonus,
今回もチェキ風ブロマイドカードがついてまいりまして、
we also have a Cheki-style bromide card included,
なんと数量限定で今回風真いろは直筆サインをですね、ありがたいことに、あのまた書かせていただけることに…
and for a limited quantity, thanks to everyone, I get to hand-sign them again...
ありがとうございます。たくさんねみなとの手元に風真の直筆サインが届くといいなと思ってくれているサインさんたちはここに届けると嬉しいです。
Thank you so much. I hope many of you will receive my handwritten signature!
よろしくお願いします。そしてなんとこちらですね、
Please look forward to it. And also, for the full set,
フルセット購入特典でボイスもついております。あの、風真がね、いつもちょっとボイスはですね、まあ先日のジュンブライドとかもそうなんですけど、ちょっとあんまりちょっと得意じゃないんですけど今回は、あの一緒に誕生日をお祝いしてもらえっていうシチュエーションでねあのその頑張らせていただきましたので、よかったら聴いてもらえると嬉しいです。
we also have a bonus voice! I'm not usually great with voice packs, but for this birthday, I worked hard on a celebratory situation...
そして、そうなんですよ！まだ実はあります！実はあるんです！それではいきますよ！せーの、どんっ！
And guess what! There's actually more! There really is! Here we go! Ready, set, boom!
はい、風真いろは公式LINEスタンプ発売決定でございまーす！いやお待たせしました！
Yes, the Kazama Iroha official LINE stamps are finally releasing! Sorry to keep you waiting!
みんな欲しいって言ってくれてたから作っていました！はい、イラストはさめある先生にお願いしました！
Everyone kept saying they wanted them, so I made them! Illustrations by Samateru-sensei!
ありがとうございます！
Thank you!
いや、こちらもですねすごくかわいいスタンプになっておりますので、ぜひぜひみなとにたくさん使っていただいて、どうやら21時ぐらいまでには帰るようになっているということなので、
These are super cute stamps too, so I hope you'll use them a lot, and it looks like we're heading home around 21:00,
ぜひ使っていただけると嬉しいです風真も使います。よろしくお願いします。待ってたありがとう！ぜひいっぱい使ってくださいね。
so I hope you use them! Kazama will use them too. Thanks for waiting!
そして、このあと21時15分頃から、えっとメンバーシップ限定のアフターライブがあります！
And right after this around 21:15, there's a membership-exclusive after-party live!
今回もですね頑張って、まだアフターライブでも歌って踊りますので、
I worked hard for this too, and I'll be singing and dancing in the after-live as well,
まだメンバーシップ入ってないよって方はぜひ加入していただけると嬉しいです。そして、メンバーシップのお知らせがもう一つあります。今回メンバーシップ限定で、今回のライブで使用した風真のソロの歌唱曲のバックスクリーンイラストの高画質バージョンを配布させていただきます！
so if you haven't joined membership yet, I'd be super happy if you did. And there's one more membership announcement. For members only, we'll be distributing high-resolution versions of the solo song background screen illustrations from this live!
りますので この後21時にコミュニティ投稿ちゃんされるはず、
It'll be posted on the community tab at 9:00 PM today,
両約と和解しているはず！
so I should have made peace with reservations!
なので、是非ですね、あの待ってる間にダウンロードしていただけると嬉しいです。よろしくお願いします！
So I'd be super happy if you could download it while you wait. Thank you so much!
はい、楽曲等のね、ご紹介でした。
Yep, that was the introduction of the song and stuff.
いや、もう本当にね、本当におあっというまに過ぎてどうしようって気持ちでいっぱいなんですけども、
Man, time really flew by so fast, I don't even know what to do with myself,
誕生日2回目みんなと一緒に迎えることができて、とってもとっても嬉しいです。ありがとうございます！
but I'm so, so happy to be able to celebrate my second birthday together with everyone. Thank you!
本当に色々ね、数多く3Dライブをやらせていただいておりますが、また成長した姿を見せれたでしょうか。
I've done quite a few 3D lives by now, but I wonder if I was able to show you a more grown-up side of me.
まだね、最初から見てないよって方はまたこのアーカイブなってからも最初から見ていただいて、もう見たけどもう回みたいて方もね、きっといらっしゃると思うので信じて、
If you haven't watched from the beginning, please check out the archive from the start, and I'm sure there are some who've seen it and want to watch it again—
もっかいみて、そしてね、他の3Dライブのアーカイブとも見比べて風真がどういうふうに成長してきたか、今一度見ていただけると嬉しいです。
please watch it again, compare it with my past 3D live archives, and see how much Kazama has grown.
それでは次最後の曲になります。心を込めて歌って踊りますので最後まで聞いてください！
And now, for our final song! I'll be singing and dancing with all my heart, so please listen till the very end!
合言葉3！
"Aikotoba III"!
皆の衆！今日は最後までライブ見てくれてありがとうございました！
Everyone! Thank you so much for watching the live all the way to the end!
一緒に誕生日を祝ってもらえてすごく嬉しかったです！これからもよろしくね！
I'm so, so happy you celebrated my birthday with me! Here's to many more!
いつかの歌も今や100万再生になって
The song from back then has now reached a million views,
僕の何万倍も年をとっちゃって
And I've grown tens of thousands of times older,
いつの間にか僕も5歳の誕生日
Before I knew it, it's already my 5th birthday.
君は僕よりも僕のこと知っているんだ
You know me even better than I know myself.
愛も恋も僕も君も好きも嫌いも全部
Love, romance, me, you, what we like, what we hate, all of it—
嘘も本当もまだまだ歌うね
Lies and truths, I'll keep on singing them all!
今までのありがとう これからもありがとう
Thank you for everything up until now, thank you for what's to come.
君に伝えたいことは それだけなんだけどさ
That's all I want to tell you, but...
なかなか上手く言えなくて 傷付けて泣いちゃって
I'm sorry I can never say it right, and that I've hurt you and made you cry.
ごめん 5年分の感謝 救世主は君のありがとう
For 5 years of gratitude, my savior is your "Thank you."
3と9をかけると 27になるの
3 multiplied by 9 makes 27.
僕を何倍しても君がいるよ
No matter how many times you multiply me, you're always right here.
それだけでこの先なんだって出来るから
Just knowing that means I can do anything from here on out!
どこへだって行こう 君を連れて歌を歌って
Let's go anywhere, taking you along, singing songs!
愛も恋も僕も君も好きも嫌いも全部
Love, romance, me, you, what we like, what we hate, all of it—
嘘も本当もまだまだ歌うね ウッイェー！
Lies and truths, I'll keep on singing them all! Woo-yeah!
君がいて…バカ。 僕がいて…バカ。
You're here... dummy. I'm here... dummy.
バカじゃない 大切なことなんだよ…バカ。
Not a dummy, it's something precious... dummy.
今までのありがとう これからもありがとう
Thank you for everything up until now, thank you for what's to come.
君に伝えたいことは それだけなんだけどさ
That's all I want to tell you, but...
なかなか上手く言えなくて 傷付けて泣いちゃって
I'm sorry I can never say it right, and that I've hurt you and made you cry.
ごめん 5年分の感謝 救世主は君のありがとう
For 5 years of gratitude, my savior is your "Thank you."
ハロー また出会えたね サヨナラ また別れて ただしまた同じ場所で出会えたんだ
Hello, we met again. Goodbye, until we part again—but we were able to meet in this same place once more.
今君が好きで　愛してくれて
I love you now, and you loved me back,
こんな歌あったねって　君が教えてくれた
You taught me that there was a song like this.
というわけで、今日は誕生日ライブ見に来てくれて、ありがとうございました！
So, thank you so much for coming to my birthday live today!
本当に楽しかったです！みんなの、ありがとう！
I really had a blast! Everyone, thank you!
バイバーイ！
Bye-bye!